So we had a look at how we test components,
Bileenleri nasl test ettiimize baktk,
let's now have a look at containers like the burger builder,
imdi hamburger reticisi gibi konteynerlere bir
how do we test these?
bakalm, bunlar nasl test edeceiz?
The tricky part about containers is that they are connected to the redux store here,
Kaplar hakkndaki zor ksm, buradaki redux deposuna balandklardr, redux maazasnn
the redux store has some external influence on this component.
bu bileen zerinde bir miktar d etkisi vardr.
If it weren't connected, testing it would just be very equal to the other components because then yes it
Eer balanmadysa, test etmek dier bileenlere ok eit olacakt nk o zaman evet, bu durumun devlete
might have state but enzyme actually also has methods to handle this, just as we have setProps,
sahip olabilecei ancak enzimin aslnda bunlar ilemek iin yntemleri olduu gibi, setProp'larmzda olduu gibi, ayn zamanda
we also have setState to simulate different states in that component.
farkl durumlar simle etmek iin setState'i de kullanyoruz bu bileen.
So the tricky thing really is the redux store,
Bu yzden gerekten zor olan ey
now the good thing is we don't really need to test the connection of this container to the redux store,
redux maazas, u anda iyi olan ey bu konteynerin balantsn redux maazasna test
we can rely on the redux store to work correctly, and then in the end we only receive data from the store
etmemize gerek yok, doru ekilde almak iin redux maazasna gvenebiliriz, ve sonunda Bu kapsaycya sahne
as props to this container.
olarak yalnzca maazadan veri alrsnz.
So we're back to the previous world,
Bu yzden bir nceki
we can just simulate props in our tests because we want to simulate different outcomes in different
dnyaya geri dndk, testlerimizde prodksiyonlar simle edebiliriz nk farkl sahnelerdeki farkl sonular simle
states of props anyways, so that we don't want to connect that to some real store,
etmek istiyoruz, bylece bunu gerek bir maazaya balamak istemiyoruz, Maazann
we don't want to test if the store passes this correctly to the component, that's the job of the connect
bunu doru ekilde bileene geirip geirmediini test etmek istersiniz, bu balant ynteminin
method
grevidir
and that's coming from a third party library,
ve nc taraf bir ktphaneden
we can rely on that to work correctly.
geliyorsa, doru ekilde almak iin bunlara gvenebiliriz.
So what we really need to do is we need to get access to the component behind this container so to
yleyse gerekten yapmamz gereken ey, bu konteynerin arkasndaki bileene eriim salamak
say
ve bu
and one convenient trick is to simply export this burger builder class,
uygun bir hilenin sadece bu burger reticisi snfn ihra etmek olmas gerektiidir,
so simply add the export statement in front of this.
bu yzden ihracat ifadesini bunun nne ekleyin.
This now gives us a named export
Bu, bize bu dosyada adlandrlm bir
in this file, burger builder which gets access to this class which is just a react component and we still
da aktarma, sadece bir tepkime bileeni olan bu snfa erien burger reticisi ve hala bizim uygulamasnda hala var olan
have the default export
ihracatmz var ama
we still have in our app but now we can write a testing file, BurgerBuilder.test.js and simply import
imdi bir test dosyas olan BurgerBuilder yazabiliyoruz. lek. js ve basite burger builder snfn
the burger builder class here with the name export from ./BurgerBuilder.
buradan ithal edilen isim ile ie aktarn. / BurgerBuilder.
This can now be rendered again with shallow and so on, just as we rendered the normal component because
Bu, tekrar normal bir bileen olduu iin, normal bileeni oluturduumuz gibi, s ve
it is just a normal component and we totally strip out the connection to redux which is what we want.
benzer ekilde yeniden oluturulabilir ve istediimiz ey olan redux balantsn tamamen keseriz.
So now with that change here, we can go to the navigation items test file and also copy the set up regarding
imdi buradaki deiiklikle, navigasyon eleri test dosyasna gidebiliriz ve ayrca enzim ve adaptr
enzyme and the adapter,
ile ilgili
let me copy all of that over to the burger builder, get rid of the imports of the navigation items
ayarlar kopyalayabiliriz, tm bunlar burger reticisine kopyalayalm, buradaki navigasyon elerinin ithalatndan kurtulun. Bunun yerine,
here instead we're importing the burger builder in that file and now we can start writing tests
bu dosyadaki burger reticisini ithal ediyoruz ve imdi burada testler
here.
yazmaya balayabiliriz.
We still do this with the describe function of course
Bunu hala tarif ileviyle yapyoruz, bu
so here we really are testing the burger builder and now to simulate this,
yzden burada burger reticisini test ediyoruz ve simdi bunu simle etmek iin, burada test
let's quickly have a look at what we could test here. If we have a look at this file,
edebileceklerimize hzlca bir gz atalm. Bu dosyaya bakacak olursak,
it would be interesting to see if we actually have build controls here,
burada gerekten yapc kontroller yapp yapmadmz grmek ilgin
if the ingredients are nonexistent because we should only render that if ingredients are passed along.
olurdu, eer malzemeler olmasalar bile, nk sadece malzemeler geilirse bunu yapmalyz.
So what we can do is we can go to that function, the describe function and we will need to import build
Yani yapabildiimiz ey, bu ileve, tanm ilevine gidebiliriz ve ina kontrollerini ie aktarmamz
controls,
gerekecek,
so let's add such an import already from ./ or let's go up actually to components burger build
bu yzden zaten byle bir ithalat ekleyelim. / ya da burger yap denetimleri bileenlerine gidip BuildControls'den
controls and import from the BuildControls.js file.
ie aktarmaya gidelim. js dosyas.
And then here, I'll again add beforeEach function to set my wrapper up, therefore I need to add this
Ve sonra, burada, daha sonra, bu sarc deikeni kullanmadan nce bu sarmalayc deikeni eklemem gerekiyor, bu
wrapper variable
yzden bu sarmalayc
before I do so and then beforeEach, wrapper should be equal to shallow again because I don't want
deikeni eklemeden nce ekleyeceim ve daha nceEt, sarc, yine derin yapmak istemediim iin yine
to do some deep rendering, I want to have an isolated unit tests as you should use it as often as possible
s olmal render, ben mmkn olduunca sk kullanmanz gerektii gibi izole bir birim testleri
and I want to shallowly render burger builder here, just like that.
istiyorum ve ben sadece bu gibi burger oluturucu s bir ekilde render istiyorum.
Now for that, we also need to import react as always, so import react from react.
Bunun iin de, her zaman olduu gibi tepkiyi ithal etmemiz gerekiyor, bu yzden ithalat, tepkiden tepki gsteriyor.
Now we can write a test with the it function and there I will describe it,
imdi bu fonksiyonla bir test
so it should render build controls when receiving ingredients.
yazabiliriz ve orada tarif edeceim, bu yzden ierik alrken yap kontrolleri oluturmal.
Now let's add as a second argument that javascript function that should get executed and now in there, I will
imdi, idam edilmesi gereken javascript ilevinin ikinci bir argman olarak ekleyelim, sadece sarcm kullanacam
simply use my wrapper
ve her eyden nce
and first of all set props and I want to set that ings prop
set aksesuar kullanacam ve bu pervane pervanesini elde etmeyi beklediimizi
we're expecting to get.
belirtmek istiyorum.
so this prop we are checking here, that ings prop we're expecting to get. Here I'll set
Bu prop biz burada kontrol ediyoruz, bu prop teklif almak iin bekliyoruz. Burada, in
ings equal to let's say a javascript object where I have salad, zero.
salata, sfr olan javascript nesnesini syleyelim.
Now with that I can use expect and wrapper and find to find my build controls, not a jsx element, just
imdi ben beklemek ve sarc kullanabilirsiniz ve bir jsx esi deil, benim ina kontrolleri bulmak iin
the type here and this should have a length of 1.
bulabilirsiniz, sadece burada yazn ve bu 1 uzunluunda olmaldr.
Let's save this file and also save the burger builder file to really export the class and in case
Bu dosyay saklayalm ve ayn zamanda snfnz ihra etmek iin burger oluturucu dosyasn saklayn ve uygulama ile ilgili bu
you're ever getting this error regarding app.test.js, remove the app.test.js file with which the project
hatay almanz durumunda. lek. js, uygulamay kaldr. lek. Projenin balad
started, it actually will mount your entire application fail due to using routing.
js dosyas, aslnda ynlendirme kullanldnda tm uygulamanzn baarsz olmasn salar.
Now you should still get one error now, that this.props.onInitIngredients is not a function, this error
imdi, u anda bir hata almalsnz. sahne. onInitIngredients bir ilev deildir,
make sense because shallow will render your component here even though it doesn't deeply do that
bu hata anlamldr nk s derinlikli bir ekilde yapmasa
and in the burger builder if you inspect it, you'll see that in componentDidMount,
bile bileeninizi buraya sacak ve burger oluturucuda incelerseniz,
we call this prop and this of course is not made available because we only set one prop, ings.
componentDidMount'ta bu prop ve Tabii ki, sadece bir pervane belirlediimiz iin kullanlabilir deil.
So to fix this, we have to add this as a prop,
Bunu dzeltmek iin bunu bir pervane olarak eklemeliyiz,
now adding it with setProps won't do the trick because that is added or that is set after the component
buna ek olarak setProp'lar ekleyerek bunu eklemeyeceiz nk bu eklenmi veya bileen oluturulduktan sonra
has been instantiated, so that's too late.
ayarlanm, bu yzden ok ge.
We have to add it here onInitIngredients and I'll set it to an empty arrow function here, to
Buraya InInInInCredients'a eklememiz gerekiyor ve bir fonksiyonun geme gerekliliini yerine getirmek iin bunu
simply fulfill the requirement of passing a function.
bir bo ok ilevine ayarlayacam.
Now with that if you save it, the test passes.
imdi bunu kaydederseniz, test geer.
If we now pass ings to be null just to check the opposite, it fails
imdi sadece tersini kontrol etmek iin null olmak zere geiler geerse, baarsz olur
and this is an example which you of course may fine tune to your need to see how you can test containers.
ve bu, elbette konteynrlar nasl test edebileceinizi grmeniz iin ince ayar yapabileceiniz bir rnektir.
You essentially strip out the component part and get rid of the connection to redux.
Esasen komponent parasn karrsnz ve yeniden balanacak balantdan kurtulursunuz.
Now speaking of redux, how do we test that then?
imdi redux'dan bahsetmiken, bunu nasl test edeceiz?